If an app updates in the background, but no one
opens it to find out, did it really happen? Notification
started off as a convenient way to notify users of
background updates. But they've grown to become a powerful standardized shortcut
to interact directly with apps in a light weight way.
Starting in Jelly Bean it was possible to expand notifications, making
them larger and containing more information. That also introduced the
concept of the rich notification, which is able to include actions
like these, to be performed on the data
included within the notification. This speeds up interaction and
helps users streamline their notification triage experience. As a
standardized UI designed specifically for conveying timely information in
limited screen space. Notifications were the obvious mechanism
to use, when Android expanded in to wearables with
Android Wear. Suddenly those rich notifications that you designed
for phones and tablets make your app wearable compatible,
for free. Don't overdo it though, there's a fine line between
useful and spammy. And it's only a couple of clicks for a
user to disable your app's notifications
permanently. So check out the instruction
that's below for links to the design guide in creating good notifications.